Inventory of the William Russell Philp collection
Hoover Institution Archives
William Russell Philp collection
1933-1952
68007
Hoover Institution Archives
8 manuscript boxes, 5 oversize boxes, 3 folios (11.1 linear feet)
The William Russell Philp collection consists of intelligence reports, interrogation reports, maps, and photographs relating to Adolf Hitler, the German military structure, national socialism, various aspects of German society during and immediately after World War II, various military campaigns of World War II (particularly preparation for the invasion of Normandy), denazification, and post-war reconstruction in Germany.
Philp, William Russell, 1892-1970
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1968.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1892 August 24 Born, Whitby, Ontario, Canada
1916 Graduated, University of Nebraska
1916-1917 Served on the Mexican border
1917 Commissioned Second Lieutenant of Field Artillery, Regular Army
1917-1919 Served in France during World War I with the 17th Field Artillery, Second U.S. Infantry Division
1919-1942 Served in various commissioned grades at various stations, including three years in Hawaii
1942 Appointed Colonel, U.S. Army
1943 Reported to U.S. Headquarters, London
1944 Assigned as Assistant Corps Artillery Officer, V Corps. Helped plan artillery support for D-Day landings on Omaha Beach, Normandy, and landed on Omaha Beach on D-Day with the V Corps.
1944-1945 Served with V Corps Headquarters through end of World War II.
1945-1952 Assigned to organize and command the European Command Intelligence Service Center at Oberursel, Germany. Completed two assignments for duty with the CIA and two with Army Intelligence.
1952 August 31 Retired
1970 January 9 Died, San Francisco, California
Colonel William Russell Philp was a career military officer, serving in the first and second world wars. Philp was largely responsible for recreating the counter-intelligence corps of the West German government after World War II. Awarded decorations include the U.S. Legion of Merit with Oak Leaf Cluster, Silver Star, Bronze Star, Purple Heart, Commendation Medal, French Legion of Honor, French Croix de Guerre with bronze star of World War I and Croix de Guerre with palm of World War II, Knights of Malta Cross of Merit, Knights of St. John Cross of Merit, and eight U.S. Campaign medals.
Scope and Content of Collection
The William Russell Philp collection includes a variety of materials, largely produced by the U.S. Army, that depict German society before, during, and immediately after World War II. Collection inlcudes interrogation reports produced by the Military Intelligence Service Center which document the July 1944 attempt on Hitler’s life. Additionally, there are reports on World War II military operations and post-war life in Germany, that cover such topics as denazification efforts, refugees, and prisoners of war. Related to the latter are two volumes of signatures and photographs of German individuals held in Allied custody for trial at Nuremberg.
The collection also contains a significant amount of material related to Philp’s involvement with planning the landings at Normandy, including aerial reconnaissance photos and an original annotated waterproof map of Normandy beaches showing the invasion strategy, as well as other maps and landing diagrams.
Also of note are albums depicting Hitler’s visit to Italy in May of 1938 and Joachim von Ribbentrop’s 1939 trip to Moscow that resulted in the signing of the Soviet-German non-aggression pact, as well as copies of Hitler’s marriage license and private and political testaments and photographs of Eva Braun and others at Hitler’s mountain retreat.
The original order, numbering, and naming of the items in the collection has been maintained.
Germany. Heer.; Hitler, Adolf, 1889-1945; Nationalsozialistische deutsche Arbeiter-Partei.; Denazification.; Germany--History--1933-1945.; Germany.; National socialism.; Reconstruction (1939-1951)--Germany.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns.; World War, 1939-1945--Germany.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Item 1. Istituto Nazionale Luce, "Il viaggio del Führer in Italia,", 1938 May 3-9 (Box 11)
  Scope and Contents note
  Blue, leather-bound photograph album (oversize).
- Item 2. Presentation copy by the Governor of Rome, Piero Colonna, of an album of sketches of Rome (Box 12)
  Red, leather-bound album, with signature of Heinrich Himmler on flyleaf. The sketches show various monuments decorated with flags and banners in honor of Hitler's visit, as seen by an Italian artist.
- Item 3. Great Britain, Foreign Office, Germany: Basic Handbook, 1944 (Box 1)
  General note
  Irregular paging.
- Item 4. Two volumes of signatures (usually with attached photograph) of German personalities in Allied custody, 1945 July-December (Box 10, Box 13)
  The two volumes are not totally identical. An identification of the prisoners' official positions is usually given. An additional folder of signatures (mostly military), Spring 1946, can be found in Box 13.
- Item 5a. Two photograph albums of Joachim von Ribbentrop's trip to Moscow, 1939 August (Box 1, Box 13)
  The photographs were taken by Gisela Pönzgen-Döhm and are of high quality. Includes shots of the signing of the Soviet-German non-aggression pact, as well as shots of Stalin, Molotov, Russian military personnel, Count von der Schulenburg (German ambassador), and Gustaf Hilger. Two negatives depicting the 1939 signing of the Soviet-German non-aggression pact by von Ribbentrop, Stalin, and Molotov can be found in Box 1.
- Item 5b. One photograph album of Joachim von Ribbentrop's activities in Berlin during the visit of the Japanese ambassador, Nobufumi Ito, 1938 February (Box 13)
- Item 6. Commemorative volume, presentation document of decoration (oak leaves for the Knight's Cross) to Paul Gildner, 1943 February (Box 9)
  Parchment with gold calligraphy and metal eagle on cover.
- Item 7. Photostatic copies of Adolf Hitler's marriage license, private testament, and political testament, as well as of a handwritten cover note by Martin Borman (dated 29 April 1945) on transferring the documents to Admiral Doenitz in Flensburg
  Includes one set of mimeographed English translations.
- Item 8a. "Eye-witness Account of the 20th July 1944,", 1945 March 29 (Box 1)
  Report summarizes in English the account by a prisoner of war (Karpinsky) who was captured by Allied Forces on 6 March 1945.
- Item 8b. "Account of the Twentieth of July Putsch by One of the Minor Conspirators,", 1945 April 11 (Box 1)
  Report summarizes in English the account by a prisoner of war (Arntz) who was captured by Allied Forces on 19 March 1945.
- Item 8c. Berlin District Interrogation Center, Consolidated Interrogation Report, "The Political and Social Background of 20 July Incident,", 1945 September 10 (Box 1)
- Item 8d. Motekat, "Concerning 20 July 1944,", undated (Box 1)
  "Reported from memory and based on testimony and the summarizing address at the trial before the People's Court."
- Item 8e. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Consolidated Interrogation Report No. 6, "Political Background of 20 July 1944,", 1947 February 11 (Box 1)
  Sources: Freiherr Rudolf von Gersdorff, Walter Hugo Gladisch, Helmuth Greiner, Dr. Karl M. Hettlage, Adolf Heusinger, Heinrich von Luettwitz, Ritter Wilhelm von Schramm, Freiherr Geyr von Schweppenburg, Graf Gerhard von Schwerin, Graf Lutz Schwerin von Krosigk, and Heribert von Strempel.
- Item 9a. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Special Report No. 36, "Adolf Hitler: A Composite Picture,", 1947 March 12 (Box 1)
  Sources: Dr. Hugo J. Blaschke, Dr. Karl Brandt, Wilhelm F. Brueckner, Karl von Eberstein, Erwin Giesing, Dr. Hans Karl von Hasselbach, Heusinger, Dr. Julius Lippert, Hans-Joachim Riecke, Dr. Paul O. Schmidt, Gerhard von Schwerin, and Lutz Schwerin von Krosigk.
- Item 9b. "Professor Morrell,", undated (Box 1)
  Typescript manuscript about Dr. Theo Morrell, written by a German in faulty English.
- Item 9c. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Consolidated Interrogation Report No. 2, "Hitler as Seen by His Doctors,", 1945 October 15 (Box 1)
  Sources: Dr. Erwin Giesing, Dr. Hanskarl von Hasselbach, and Dr. Karl Brandt. Includes declassified records returned to file after December 2015.
- Item 9d. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Consolidated Interrogation Report No. 4, "Hitler as Seen by His Doctors,", 1945 November 29 (Box 1)
  Sources: Dr. Theo Morrell, Dr. Erwin Giesing, Dr. Walter Loehlein, Dr. Karl Weber, Dr. A. Nissle, and Dr. E. Brinkmann. Primarily based on an interview with Dr. Theo Morrell. Annexes include medical reports and X-ray pictures of Hitler's head taken in September 1944 (in separate folio) when he was treated for ear trouble, a possible result of the explosion of 20 July 1944. Includes declassified records returned to file after December 2015.
- Item 9e. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Final Interrogation Report No. 31, "Hitler's Teeth,", 1946 February 5 (Box 1)
  Source: Dr. Hugo Johannes Blaschke. Includes declassified records returned to file after December 2015.
- Item 10. Eva Braun snapshots, undated (Box 2)
  Six photographs of Eva Braun, Adolf Hitler, and others at Hitler's mountain retreat. Additionally, there are enlargements of two of the photographs.
- Item 11. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, The German General Staff Series, 1945 December 28 (Box 2)
  - The History of the German General Staff from 1806 to 1934 by Walter Warlimont, Gen. d.Art
  - The German General Staff Since World War I by Graf Gerhard von Schwerin, Gen. d.Pztr
  - The Character of the German General Staff from 1923 to 1945 by Karl Allmendinger, Gen. d.Inf
  - The Political Attitude of the German General Staff since 1920 by Walter Warlimont, Gen. d.Art
  - National Socialism and the German General Staff by Wilhelm Ritter von Schramm, Major d.R
  - The Political Attitude and Military Aptitude of the Younger Generation of General Staff Officers by Friedrich Berendsen, Oberst d.Kav, 1945 December 28
  - The Attitude of the General Staff Toward Technology by Adolf Heusinger, Gen. Lt.d.Inf
  - The German General Staff and Technical Developments by Wilhelm Petersen, Gen. Maj. d.Pi
  - The Decline in Unity and Influence of the German General Staff by Bogislaw von Bonin, Oberst d.Pztr
- Item 12. Cigaretten Bilderdienst, Deutschland erwacht: Werden, Kampf und Sieg der NSDAP, 1933 (Box 2)
  Text by Wilfred Bade, photographs by Heinrich Hoffmann.
- Item 13. Heeresgruppe Nord, "Der Feldzug gegen die Sowjet-Union der Heeresgruppe Nord, Kriegsjahr 1943" (Box 9)
  Commemorative volume issued by the Oberkommando of the Wehrmacht containing detailed maps for the Russian campaign of Heeresgruppe (Army Group) Nord (copy 54).
- Item 14a. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Intermediate Interrogation Report No. 12, "Austria,", 1945 October 3 (Box 2)
  Source: Franz von Papen.
- Item 14b. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Final Interrogation Report No. 12, "Balancing the Accounts,", 1945 October 27 (Box 2)
- Item 15a. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Re-Interrogation Report No. 9, "The Führer's Headquarters,", 1945 October 24 (Box 2)
  Source: Walter Warlimont.
- Item 15b. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Re-Interrogation Report No. 15, "A Summary of the Campaign in Russia 1941-1944,", 1946 February 1 (Box 2)
  Source: Adolf Heusinger.
- Item 15c. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Final Interrogation Report No. 3, "Haushofer and the Influence of His Geopolitical Theories,", 1945 September 22 (Box 2)
  Source: Karl Haushofer.
- Item 15d. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Final Interrogation Report No. 14, "Notes on World War II,", 1945 November 1 (Box 2)
  Source: Freiherr von Schweppenburg Geyr.
- Item 15e. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Final Interrogation Report No. 123, "Nazi Church Politics,", 1947 January 9 (Box 2)
  Source: Albert Hartl.
- Item 15f. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Intermediate Interrogation Report No. 29, "Critical Study of Experiences Gained in German Armored Operations,", 1946 February 8 (Box 3)
  Source: Fritz Bayerlein.
- Item 15g. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Scavenger Special Report No. 20, "Panzer Lehr Division,", 1945 June 23 (Box 3)
- Item 16. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, U Report No. 2, "Errors of the German Policy in the Ukraine (1941-1944),", 1947 June 12 (Box 3)
  Sources: "Prominent German and Ukrainian personalities in the German occupation of the Ukraine" and "[n]umerous documents of the East Ministry (Ostministerium-Rosenberg), of military and civilian administrative offices, and of key Ukrainians."
- Item 17a. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, U Project Report No. 1, "German Experiences in the Seizure of Agricultural Products and the Struggle Against the Black Market in the Ukraine in the Years 1941-1944,", 1947 May 15 (Box 3)
  Source: "German documents and records, reports of undercover agents and of former German agricultural and economic experts." Includes declassified records returned to file after December 2015.
- Item 17b. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Intermediate Interrogation Report No. 36, "Agricultural Technology and the RKTL,", 1946 September 5 (Box 3)
  Source: Hans Joachim Ernst Riecke.
- Item 17c. American report on German agriculture, undated (Box 3)
- Item 18. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Final Interrogation Report No. 137, report on Communist agent Günter Heinz Manfred Tuttas, 1947 March 27 (Box 3)
- Item 19. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Special Report No. 29, "The Mental Attitude of German Prisoners of War,", 1947 February 20 (Box 3)
  Source: Hans-Gottfried von Watzdorf.
- Item 20. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Special Report No. 32, "Operations and Experiences of Frontaufklärung (FA) III Ost During the Eastern Campaign,", 1947 January 27 (Box 3)
  Source: former chief of the German Abwehr Leitstelle III Ost (formerly Walli III) and one of his former assistants.
- Item 21. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Reinterrogation Report No. 2, "Origin and Growth of National Socialism and National Socialism and the German People,", 1945 September 1 (Box 3)
  Source: Graf Lutz Schwerin von Krosigk.
- Item 22. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Special Report No. 42, "The Counterintelligence Organization 'SMERSH' of the Red Army,", 1947 March 24 (Box 3)
  Source: member of the German Abwehr's Leitsetelle III Ost.
- Item 23a. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Special Interrogation Report No. 26, Annex II, "GZI,", 1947 February 26 (Box 3)
  Glowny Zarzad Informacji Wojska Polskiego (Central Office of the Information Services of the Polish Army). Also known as the Informacji. Source: Sergius Naumovich Perling. Photocopy.
- Item 23b. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Special Interrogation Report No. 26, Annex III, "The Serov Group,", 1947 April 12 (Box 3)
  Photocopy.
- Item 24. Detailed Interrogation Report, "A Study of the Rise of Naziism,", 1945 June 23 (Box 3)
  Source: Graf Gerhard von Schwerin.
- Item 25. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Special Report No. 28, interrogation of Dimitri Tivin, NKVD agent, 1946 December 23 (Box 3)
- Item 26. Headquarters, 12th Army Group, Interrogation Center, Intermediate Interrogation Report, interrogation of Ernst Kaltenbrunner, chief of the RHSA, 1945 June 28 (Box 4)
- Item 27. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Reinterrogation Report No. 7, "Goering's Views on Certain Aspects of German Foreign Policy,", 1945 October 24 (Box 4)
  Source: Hermann Goering.
- Item 28. CLOSED
- Item 29a. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Preliminary Interrogation Report No. 35, interrogation of Heribert Hugo von Strempel, Secretary in the Foreign Office, 1945 December 14 (Box 4)
- Item 29b. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, Intermediate Interrogation Report No. 37, interrogation of Kurt Henschel, employee of the German Foreign Service, 1945 December 18 (Box 4)
- Item 30. "Report on the Further Development in the Eastern Zone,", 1946 September (Box 4)
  Report by Christian Geiger-Helbe with cover letters and documentary annexes on conditions in the Soviet zone of occupation. Includes declassified records returned to file after December 2015.
- Item 31. Office of the United States High Commissioner for Germany, Office of the Land Commissioner for Hesse, Intelligence Division, "Periodic Intelligence Report for the Week Ending 2400 Hours, January 2, 1950 (Summary No. 178),", 1950 January 4 (Box 4)
- Item 32. Report on border traffic between the border refugee Camp Hof-Moschendorf (U.S. Zone) and the Soviet Zone, with report on morale, circa 1947 January (Box 4)
- Item 33a. "Resolve of the Politburo of the WKPB [All-Russian Committee of the Party of Bolsheviks],", 1934-1935 (Box 4)
  Typescript drafts with handwritten annotations from Mr. Silver to Col. Philp dated 10 November 1934, 14 November 1934, 23 November 1934, 26 November 1934, 7 January 1935, and 5 February 1935.
- Item 33b. "Some Remarks on 'Sources of Soviet Conduct' by Mr. X," E. Mylkevich, 1947 (Box 4)
  Includes cover letter by Mylkevich to Col. Philp, dated 18 September 1947 [though this would seem to be incorrect, given that the letter mentions an editorial of 10 October 1947].
- Item 33c. "Political Notes on the USSR and US" [E. Mylkevich], 1947 August (Box 4)
- Item 33d. "Comments on Mr. John Fischer's Articles on Soviet Life [New York Herald Tribune], Nov. 6-10, 1946," E. Mylkevitch, 1946 December 10 (Box 4)
  Includes original articles.
- Item 33d. Letter from E. Mylkevich to Walter Lippmann re Soviet Union, 1946 December 1 (Box 4)
  Lippmann was the political correspondent for the New York Herald Tribune.
- Item 34. Documents from Raymond Jadin, Prosecuting Justice, Military Tribunal of Strasbourg, 1946-1947 (Box 4)
  Includes cover letter dated 21 December 1947 indicating enclosures of two examinations of ex-Gauleiter [Robert] Wagner (5 February and 11 March 1946), the examination of Magistrate [Friedrich Karl] Simon (28 January 1946), the examination of Marshall [Wilhelm] Keitel (12 April 1946), and letters of congratulations to Jadin from his military chiefs (dated 14 May 15 November 1946).
- Item 35a. Headquarters, United States Forces in the European Theater, Military Intelligence Service Center, "United State, Federal State, Confederacy," Lutz Schwerin von Korsigk, Minister of Finance, circa 1947 (Box 4)
  Includes cover memorandum dated 31 January 1947, "Report on German Political History," indicating that the report was originaly written in German.
- Item 35b. "Proposals for Denazification,", undated (Box 4)
- Item 35c. Extract from "Disease of Persecution," Dr. W. Stapel, undated (Box 4)
- Item 35d. "Characteristics of the German Officials,", undated (Box 4)
- Item 35e. "The Difficulties of the Church in Germany,", undated (Box 4)
- Item 35f. "Law Suits Against War-Criminals,", undated (Box 4)
  Also includes a typescript about an encounter with a Russian woman on a train.
- Item 35g. "Reparations,", undated (Box 4)
- Item 36a. Collection Section, United States Forces in the European Theater, 7707 European Command Intelligence Center, "Interrogation of Illegal Border Crossers,", 1952 July 22 (Box 4)
- Item 36b. "Exploitation of PW Returnees and Illegal Border Crossers, Progress Report for June 1952,", 1952 July 10 (Box 4)
- Item 36c. United States Forces in the European Theater, 7707 European Command Intelligence Center, "Effectiveness and Value of an IBC Exploitation Program,", 1952 February 14 (Box 4)
- Item 36d. "Report on Conditions Found in Straubing and Nuremberg (Camp Valka) as They Affect the Scientific and Technical Intelligence Collection Effort by Mr. J. L. Boughal, Mr. J. A. Fuhrken, and Mr. J. C. Pallenberg,", 1951 November 5 (Box 4)
  There is a handwritten date on the front of 4 February 1952.
- Item 36e. "Conditions Affecting the Exploitation of German IBCs for Scientific and Technical Intelligence,", 1952 February 4 (Box 4)
- Item 37. Office of Military Government for Germany (U.S.), Office of the Military Governor, "Law for Liberation from National Socialism and Militarism,", 1946 April 29 (Box 4)
- Item 38. Allied Control Authority, Coordinating Committee, Directive No. 38, "Arrest and Punishment of War Criminals, Nazis and Militarists and the Internment, Control, and Surveillance of Politically Dangerous Germans,", 1946 October 14 (Box 4)
- Item 39. Office of Military Government for Germany (U.S.), Information Services Division, Opinion Surveys Branch, Report No. 160, "Germans Consider the Withdrawal of the Occupying Powers,", 1949 February 23 (Box 4)
- Item 40. Annex No. 1 to Corps Artillery Intelligence Report No. 156, "Special Report: The Odyssey of Goetz von Berlichingen,", 1944 (Box 4)
  Report from memory of a staff officer of the 17th SS Pz. Gren. Division.
- Item 41. "Die Familien Katastrophe der Internierten: Eine 1000 Mann Umfrage,", circa 1947 (Box 4)
  Related to Camp 74 at Ludwigsburg. Includes English translation ("Internees' Family Troubles: An Enquiry Amongst 1000 Internees").
- Item 42. Fragment of a report on German youth, undated (Box 4)